Guide to the Mabel Brady Garvan Institute of American Arts and Crafts, Yale University, Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Mabel Brady Garvan Institute of American Arts and Crafts, Yale University, records
1562-1937
RU 561
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5.5
The records consist of material relating to the study of the Lee plantation conducted by the Mabel Brady Garvan Institute of American Arts and Crafts at Yale. Included are the Stratford survey report, financial records, background materials, correspondence, and subject and administrative files.
Yale University. Mabel Brady Garvan Institute of American Arts and Crafts
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 37 (YRG 37), Records of associations, institutes, centers, and organizations affiliated with Yale University.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the materials is partially restricted. See inventory for details.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of material relating to the study of the Lee plantation conducted by the Mabel Brady Garvan Institute of American Arts and Crafts at Yale. Included are the Stratford survey report, financial records, background materials, correspondence, and subject and administrative files.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by accession.
Art museums; College art museums; Handicraft; Lee, Annie Carter, 1839-1862; Lee, Charles Carter, 1798-1871; Lee, Henry, 1756-1818; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; Lee family; Shippen family; Yale University. Mabel Brady Garvan Institute of American Arts and Crafts
- Mabel Brady Garvan Institute of American Arts & Crafts records, Accession 19ND-A-161
  - THE STRATFORD SURVEY GENERAL REPORT, 1931; Series I
    - Volume One (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Volume Two (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
    - Volume Three (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - THE STRATFORD SURVEY: FINANCIAL RECORDS, 1931; Series II
    - Accounting for expenses: September, October, November Trail Balance (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Bank statements with vouchers (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Check and deposit books (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Expense books (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - BACKGROUND MATERIAL, 1779-1935; Series III
    - Ann Carter Lee, second wife of General Henry Lee, 1805-1829 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - I. Five original autographed letters from Ann Carter Lee to members of her family. Rocky Mount collection. Proof read. Photostats made. (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - II. Birth record of children in Lee Family Bible. Owned by Ann Lee' great-granddaughter, Mrs. Alice Lee Harvie of Richmond, Va. Proof read. (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - III. Copies of two letters to her son Sydney Smith Lee. Printed in Douglas Freeman's R.E.Lee. Owner: Mrs. Marian Oliver of Shirley. Not photostated. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Charles Carter Lee, 1831-1849 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Charles Carter Lee, 1829-1837 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - General Henry Lee (Light-Horse Harry Lee), 1785-1816 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Typed Copies of original letters and documents found by Ethel Armes in chest at Rocky Mount, Virginia. Proof read. Photostats made. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Major Henry Lee, 1810-1834 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Typed Copies of his correspondence with his brother, Charles Carter Lee, and others. Some have not been proof read or photostated. Rocky Mount collection. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Major Henry Lee, 1816-1821 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Major Henry Lee, 1821 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Major Henry Lee, 1814-1835 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - II. Typed copies of series of letters. Proofread. Photostated. Rocky Mount Collection. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Major Henry Lee, 1827-1837 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - III. Typed copies of series of letters and miscellaneous notes. Proofread. Photostated. Rocky Mount Collection. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Mary Custis Lee (Mrs. Robert E. Lee), 1869-1871 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Robert E. Lee, 1868 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - John Leeds material: photostats (from Ethel Armes Collection), 1774 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - President Roosevelt's foreword to by Ethel Armes, and correspondence with R. Walton Moore, Assistant Secretary of State., 1935 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - OVERSIZE BACKGROUND MATERIAL PHOTOSTATS AND TYPEWRITTEN COPIES, 1562-1937; Series IV
    - The Lee Pedigree: Recording the English ancestry of the Virginia Lees. Prepared by H. Edward Forrest, Shrewsbury. Accepted by the College of Heralds, London, England, November 1, 1933, under signature of Arthur Cochrane, Clarencaux, King of Arms. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Additions, original letters in Huntington Library, New York Public Library and others, 1779-1927, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Sydney Smith Lee, 1869 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Lucy Ludwell Paradise, Ludwell and Lee Families. Statement by Thomas Jefferson, 1788 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Additions. Nancy Shippen: verse addresses to her from Louis Guillaume Otto, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Maps of Virginia, 1651-1775 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Document: pre-revolutionary, 1768-1775 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Record of Stewart Family of Stratford and King George County, Virginia, 1562 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Stratford Hall: Declaration of Assurance, December 26, 1795, showing plat of (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Stratford buildings, number, location, dimensions, nomenclature, materials of construction and monetary value (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Declaration of Assurance, 1805 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Stratford Hall: Insurance Plats Major Henry Lee, 1816 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Stratford Hall: Declaration of Assurance Taken out by George Ball for comparative purposes, 1811 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Stratford Hall Library: Facsimiles of title pages and prefaces of some of the books of Stratford Hall, 1722-1822 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Stratford Hall: Modern architectural plans for house and garden, 1930-1932 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Estates of the Lee Family, and Carters: Plan of the Castle, Green Spring Virginia Comparative plans of the Capitol at Williamsburg and of Stratford Hall, 1648 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Descriptions of Stratford Ha11, Mt. Pleasant, Chantilly (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Old Menokin House, Carotoman (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Stratford Hall: furnishings (Masonic emblems), 1861 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Mary Custis Lee (Mrs. Robert E. Lee): Letters from. 1834-1869, 1834-1871 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Charles Carter Lee:, 1868 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Letter to Robert E. Lee (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Letter to Mrs. Robert E. Lee (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Letter to M. Guizot (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Robert E. Lee: Documents and Letters, 1840-1865 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - The Lee Pedigree: Recording the English ancestry of the Virginia Lees, 1725-1924 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Robert E. Lee: Account of his death and burial (1807-1870) (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - George Washigton Parke Curtiss Lee (son of Robert E. Lee): Letter from Lee to R. A. Brock describing horses owned by General Robert E. Lee. Document's signed by G.W.P.C. Lee, 1891 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Pennsylvania: An Act to revive the incorporation of subscribers to the Bank of North America, 1787 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Permanent File: Transcriptions of original letters and photostats, 1750-1870 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Richard Henry Lee, 1775-1776 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Declaration of Independence (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Letter of T. Cushing to R. H. Lee (copy) (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Letter of T. Jefferson to R. H. Lee (copy) (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Mrs George Izard (Elizabeth Carter Izard, wife of Thomas Lee Shippen), 1824 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Will of Gawen Corbin, husband of Hannah Lee, 1759 (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - The Hannah Lee Coach, 1760 (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - A.L.s to Alice Lee Shippen (her sister) from Peckatone, Westmoreland County, Virginia, 1780? (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - Alice Lee Shippen, daughter of Thomas Lee, president of Virginia, 1778, 1809, 1813 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - Dr. William Shippen: Papers from his mother, his aunt and Dr. Storrow, 1799-1824 (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - Lucy Grymes Lee Carter: Original letters from Mrs. Bernard M. Carter (Lucy Grymes Lee, daughter of Light-Horse Harry Lee) to Alice Lee Shippen, her great aunt, 1798-1813 (Box 5, Folder 52)
    - Francis Lightfoot Lee, 1734-1797 (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - Arthur Lee, 1740-1792 (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - General Henry Lee
      - Letters to him from George Washington and General Nathaniel Green, 1779-1783 (Box 5, Folder 55)
      - Source of material for his Memoirs. Notes and memoranda from Colonel John Eager Howard, 1780-1781 (Box 5, Folder 56)
      - Letters to his brother Richard Bland Lee and to his mother-in-law Mrs. Philip Richard Fendell of Alexandria, Virginia, 1786 (Box 5, Folder 57)
      - Letters from William Goddard containing source data for Lee's Memoirs, 1786-1810 (Box 5, Folder 58)
      - Letter to General Henry Lee from William Lee. Original document (Identure), 1713-1809 (Box 5, Folder 59)
      - Letters from Rufus King and G. K. Taylor, 1795, 1798 (Box 5, Folder 60)
      - Deed signed by John James Maund, 1796 (Box 5, Folder 60)
      - Notes on Randall's, 1798 (Box 5, Folder 61)
      - Indenture between Philip R. Fendall and Henry Lee, 1804 (Box 5, Folder 61)
      - Legal document with his son and Robert Sanford, 1810 (Box 5, Folder 61)
      - Original autographed letter (copy) from his father General Henry Lee, 1816 (Box 5, Folder 61)
      - Revolution memoirs, 1809 (Box 5, Folder 62)
      - Biographical notes about General Nathaniel Greene and General Linclon for Lee's, 1808-1810 (Box 5, Folder 63)
      - Source material for his, 1809-1816 (Box 5, Folder 64)
      - Biographical notes about Colonel Christopher Greene, 1810 (Box 5, Folder 65)
      - Historical data contributed by Colonel Davie to Lee's, 1810 (Box 5, Folder 66)
      - Letters from Lee to W. R. Davie (Box 5, Folder 66)
      - Data contributed by Nathaniel Pendleton for Lee's, 1811 (Box 5, Folder 67)
      - Henry Lee, father of General Henry Lee, 1779 (Box 5, Folder 68)
      - Autographed letter (copy) to President Madison Letters to his sons Charles Carter Lee and Henry Lee, and to his wife Ann Carter Lee, 1813 (Box 5, Folder 69)
      - Ann Carter Lee, wife of General Henry Lee, 1805-1829 (Box 5, Folder 70)
    - Major Henry Lee
      - Source references authenticating Lee's attendence at Washington & Lee University and the College of William and Mary, 1809 (Box 5, Folder 71)
      - Series of letters to him (typed), 1811-1834 (Box 5, Folder 72)
      - Series of letters to him, 1811-1836 (Box 5, Folder 73)
      - Letter to him from General James Wilkinson, 1814 (Box 5, Folder 74)
      - Letters, autographed, from F.W. Gilmer Letter from Havanna, 1816 (Box 5, Folder 75)
      - Notice of his candidacy for position of Member of Congress for the counties of Westmoreland, etc., 1816-1821 (Box 5, Folder 76)
      - Certificate of his election to the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia, 1816 (Box 5, Folder 77)
      - Letter from James Madison, 1833 (Box 5, Folder 77)
      - Act for relief of Henry Lee, 1836 (Box 5, Folder 77)
      - His letter to Andrew Jackson, 1825 (Box 5, Folder 78)
      - Legal opinions about possession and uses of negroes, 1825 (Box 5, Folder 79)
      - Letter to his wife, 1825? (Box 5, Folder 80)
      - Autographed letter from Mrs. Andrew Jackson, undated (Box 5, Folder 80)
      - Letter from his brother Charles Carter Lee, 1829 (Box 5, Folder 80)
      - His appointment as Counsul General, 1829 (Box 5, Folder 81)
      - Diary of events in Algiers, official record kept by Consul General (Incomplete), 1829-1830 (Box 5, Folder 81)
      - Copy by Richard T. Brown of Lee's letter to Honorable John Tyler, 1833 (Box 5, Folder 82)
      - Series of seven letters to his brother Charles Carter Lee, 1829-1833 (Box 5, Folder 83)
      - Series of Twelve letters to Major Henry Lee, 1816-1835 (Box 5, Folder 84)
      - Indenture made between Henry V. Sommerville and Henry Lee, Ann R. Lee, his wife and Charles Carter Lee, 1829 (Box 5, Folder 84)
      - Newspaper clippings found in Major Henry Lee's collection of papers, death notice, Undated, 1837 (Box 5, Folder 85)